Dr. Andrew John Lowe

↑ Nagysándor József utca 8. I./4, 1195 Budapest, Hungary · ★ Willing to relocate andrew.john.lowe@gmail.com · in linkedin.com/in/andrewjohnlowe · ⑤ andrewjohnlowe

PROFESSIONAL PROFILE

I am a British data scientist with 6 years' professional experience in consulting for diverse business clients and over 15 years' experience working at the forefront of scientific research within large international collaborations. I have a PhD in particle physics, spent several years based at CERN in Geneva and was a member of the team that discovered the Higgs boson. My core competencies include statistical data analysis, machine learning, software development, mathematical modelling, data visualisation and interpretation of results. I am a co-author of over 500 peer-reviewed scientific publications and have spoken in numerous international workshops and conferences.

EMPLOYMENT

Jun. 2017– present

Data Scientist

EPAM Systems Inc., Hungary

Acted as a consultant, working directly and collaboratively with clients on a range of projects:

• London Stock Exchange Group (May 2018–May 2023) (Originally Thomson Reuters Finance & Risk, became Refinitiv in Oct. 2018, which merged with LSEG in Feb. 2021.)

Single-handedly devised, implemented and maintained software in R and Python to anonymise sensitive personal data to ensure compliance with EU GDPR data protection and privacy regulations, thereby derisking a \$250 million per annum revenue stream for the client business. The software ingests, cleans and analyses the data and uses machine learning to generate a structurally and statistically identical synthetic dataset with strong privacy guarantees. Established best practices to help the client business meet their GDPR obligations. Provided guidance and leadership on data privacy issues. Created and shared recommendations to audiences of varying technical levels. Mentored a junior data scientist. Conducted research and provided expert advice to help define strategy with regards to reducing the client's carbon footprint from computing use, thereby helping them meet their environmental sustainability goals. Co-author of a green software architecture & engineering guide.

• Bayer AG (Nov. 2017–Feb. 2018)

Built ETL processes using KNIME for automated Excel financial report generation. Reduced report generation time from over 24 hours to under 2 hours.

• UBS Wealth Management Americas (Jul. 2017–Sep. 2017)

Generated synthetic training data for cloud-hosted chatbot to process customer service requests.

Sept. 2013– May 2017

Scientific Research Fellow

Wigner Research Centre for Physics, Hungarian Academy of Sciences, Hungary

Performed statistical data analysis for the ALICE experiment at CERN, which recreates conditions that are believed to have existed a fraction of a second after the Big Bang. Used state-of-the-art machine learning to develop predictive classification algorithms for recognising particles based on their decay properties. Engaged with local data science community via public outreach talks and conference presentations.

Apr. 2010– Oct. 2012

Postdoctoral Fellow, Deputy Team Leader

California State University, Fresno, USA (based 100% at CERN, Switzerland)

Systematically investigated the potential benefit of hundreds of different predictor variables for a range of data-mining analyses using Monte Carlo simulations written in C++. Found several new variables that provide significant improvements in sensitivity for a variety of Higgs boson and new particle searches, thereby vastly reducing the amount of expensive experiment running time required to collect sufficient data for offline analysis. Developed and productionised core software and algorithms for real-time data analysis.

Feb. 2008- Postdoctoral Fellow

Aug. 2009 Indiana University, USA (based 100% at CERN, Switzerland)

Developed an algorithm in C++ and Python for real-time particle identification in streaming data at an input rate of 1 GB/s. Optimised algorithm parameters and achieved excellent performance. This algorithm underpins a large part of the ATLAS experiment's physics programme by providing the data used by about 3000 physicists for many analyses. It has been used in production for data-taking since 2010 and has processed tens of petabytes of data for subsequent offline analysis.

Mar. 1998– Assistant Research Scientist

Sept. 2000 Centre for Time Metrology, National Physical Laboratory (NPL), UK

Provided technical and administrative support to a range of key activities relating to the maintenance and dissemination of the UK's national time scale.

EDUCATION

2001–2008 PhD Particle Physics

Royal Holloway, University of London, UK (including 17 months at CERN, Switzerland) Thesis title: Performance and robustness studies of the trigger for the ATLAS experiment

Played a key role in the development of the core software and algorithms in C++ for a real-time multi-stage cascade classifier that filters and reduces the collision event data rate from $60\,\text{TB/s}$ to a manageable $300\,\text{MB/s}$ which can be written to permanent storage. Performed detailed time profiling of the core software and devised improvements that made it 8 times faster, thus meeting a critical requirement of the system. Wrote software that was used in the discovery of the Higgs boson.

2000–2001 MSc Particle Physics

Royal Holloway, University of London, UK Thesis title: Light Higgs $(H \rightarrow b\bar{b})$ at the LHC

Investigated the search potential of the $H \to b\bar{b}$ decay channel for a light Higgs boson using the ATLAS detector at CERN. This was the first data-mining analysis of this type to be performed entirely in C++, and as such served as an example for other researchers to follow.

1993–1996 BSc (Hons) Physics

Royal Holloway, University of London, UK

TRANSFERABLE SKILLS

• Communication:

Can work closely with clients as a consultant and communicate effectively with other departments and business stakeholders to discuss complex data-driven findings and technical specifications. Can translate client requirements into highly specified project documentation. Invited speaker at numerous international conferences. Visual storytelling and data visualization best practices. Teamwork in a collaboration of about 3000 people.

• Problem solving:

Capacity to lead independent research, understand and dissect complex problems and find creative solutions.

• Project management:

Accustomed to handling parallel projects with strict deadlines, both on-site and remotely. Knowledge of Agile and Waterfall software development methodologies. Experienced in leading project meetings.

COMPUTING SKILLS

- Programming languages: Python (NumPy, Pandas, Scikit-Learn, Matplotlib, Seaborn, etc.), R, SQL, C++, Octave
- Data mining software: KNIME, Weka, XGBoost, H₂O, caret, ROOT
- Data visualisation: ggplot2, Plotly, TIBCO Spotfire, Tableau, flexdashboard, Shiny
- Notebooks/Documentation: Jupyter, Google Colab, R Markdown, LATEX
- Software development: Docker, Git/GitHub/GitLab, Jira, RStudio, UML, Valgrind, Visual Studio Code
- Operating systems: Unix, Linux, Microsoft Windows
- Other: object-oriented analysis and design, CPU and time profiling, code optimisation, memory debugging.